<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Species>
  <Key>AQUA</Key>
  <Name>Aqualish</Name>
  <Description>
    [H4]Aqualish[h4]
    The Aqualish are tusked bipeds from the planet Ando
    whose appearance combined aspects of arachnids and
    pinniped aquatic mammals. Aqualish had a reputation
    for being nasty, crude and aggressive, and generally
    pursued off-world careers as mercenaries, bounty
    hunters, and pirates. One of the most infamous such
    Aqualish was the smuggler Ponda Baba.
    [P][B]Physiology:[b]
    An amphibious species native to the planet Ando, the
    Aqualish people are made up of three distinct races
    which included the Aquala, the Ualaq and the Quara.
    Although they all had their differences, their
    baseline genetic structure was the same and their
    appearances did not vary so drastically as to
    characterize them as different species. All Aqualish
    have two facial tusks which curved down over their
    mouths; a trait which adds to their appearance as
    arachnids. Indeed, the Aqualish have some arachnid
    genetic material in their distant past, as
    demonstrative in their relationship with the Harch
    species. These facial tusks are highly sensitive
    to heat and cold, and were used for cracking open
    the hard shells of shellfish or burrowing through
    the swampy loam of their homeworld.
    [P][B]Society:[b]
    The Aquala hate their Quara relatives, as they
    blame them for the image the Aqualish had on the
    galaxy as thugs. Because of this the latter
    subspecies are considered pariahs on Ando, which
    has a lower population of Aqualish than the galaxy
    itself. All three Aqualish subspecies speak
    mutually intelligible dialects of the same language.
    Quarrelsome and thug-like, the Aqualish culture
    revolves around aggression and toughness, with
    diplomacy being one of their weakest attributes.
    [P][B]Homeworld:[b]
    Ando, the homeworld of the Aqualish, is an oceanic
    planet located in the Ando system of the Mid Rim.  The
    sea covers 95% of the world.  The majority of the
    world's islands are sustained by a decaying swamp
    ecosystem and covered in steamy mist.
    [P][B]Language:[b]
    Aqualish is the official language of the planet 
    Ando, spoken by the Aqualish species. The three 
    subspecies of Aqualish—Aquala, Quara and Ualaq—each 
    have a different dialect. However, these regionalisms 
    are so similar that they are easily understood by 
    speakers of the separate dialects.
    [P]Aqualish vocal cords cause harsh guttural 
    sounds, which are common in the Aqualish language, 
    but uncommon in Basic. If an Aqualish speaks Galactic 
    Basic Standard, it sounds coarse and brutish. Most 
    Aqualish do not learn Basic unless they needed to, 
    which usually means they have been forced to leave 
    their homeworld.
  </Description>
  <Source>Unofficial Species Menagerie 2.0</Source>
  <StartingChars>
    <Brawn>2</Brawn>
    <Agility>2</Agility>
    <Intellect>2</Intellect>
    <Cunning>2</Cunning>
    <Willpower>2</Willpower>
    <Presence>2</Presence>
  </StartingChars>
  <StartingAttrs>
    <WoundThreshold>12</WoundThreshold>
    <StrainThreshold>10</StrainThreshold>
    <Experience>100</Experience>
  </StartingAttrs>
  <SkillModifiers>
    <SkillModifier>
      <Key>COERC</Key>
      <RankStart>1</RankStart>
      <RankLimit>2</RankLimit>
    </SkillModifier>
  </SkillModifiers>
  <OptionChoices>
    <OptionChoice>
      <Key>AQUASWIM</Key>
      <Name>Swimming</Name>
      <Options>
        <Option>
          <Key>AQUASWIMOP</Key>
          <Name>Natural Swimmers</Name>
          <Description>Aqualish gain a [BOOST] on all
          Athletics checks made to swim.</Description>
        </Option>
      </Options>
    </OptionChoice>
    <OptionChoice>
      <Key>AQUASUB</Key>
      <Name>Subspecies</Name>
      <Options>
        <Option>
          <Key>AQUASUBAQ</Key>
          <Name>Aquala</Name>
          <Description>
            The Aquala subspecies is considered to be the
            baseline Aqualish breed. Having finned hands and
            two bulbous black eyes, the Aquala are unable to
            manipulate most machinery or equipment developed
            by the galaxy's many species which designed these
            tools for beings with digits. As a result, Aquala
            tend to remain on their homeworld in greater
            numbers then either of the other subspecies.
          </Description>
        </Option>
        <Option>
          <Key>AQUASUBQU</Key>
          <Name>Quara</Name>
          <Description>
            The Quara have developed clawed,
            five-fingered hands and like the Aquala have two eyes.
            Combined with the Ualaq, the Quara make up only ten
            percent of the Aqualish population. This is due to
            their ability to use equipment offworld designed for
            fingered species; Thus, they are the subspecies
            more commonly found off-world.
          </Description>
        </Option>
        <Option>
          <Key>AQUASUBUA</Key>
          <Name>Ualaq</Name>
          <Description>
            The Ualaq,
            considered by some specialists to be the result
            of genetic mutation, have four eyes instead of
            two and fingered hands which varied from three to
            five digits on each. The least common subspecies,
            the Ualaq often times journeyed far from Ando to
            avoid discrimination by the Aquala.
          </Description>
        </Option>
      </Options>
    </OptionChoice>  
  </OptionChoices>
</Species>
